Joshua E. Lambert, Ph.D.

🔇 jelambert.com 🔀 joshuae.lambert@gmail.com in in/joshuaelambert/ 💆 twitter.com/jelambert_

ABOUT

I am a Postdoctoral Scholar skilled in computational social science methods. I have experience with econometric methods, natural language processing, machine learning, and geospatial analysis. I have published popular and scholarly work that has looked at various conflict dynamics, political instability, and leader psychology utilizing both qualitative and quantitative methods.

EDUCATION

Ph.D., Security Studies

University of Central Florida, Orlando, FL, August 2020 "Food, Familiarity, and Forecasting: Modeling Coups with Computational Methods"

M.A.,Political Science

University of New Orleans, New Orleans, LA, December 2015 Concentration: International Relations

B.A., Political Science

Auburn University, Auburn, AL, May 2014 Minor: Religious Studies

WORK EXPERIENCE

Postdoctoral Scholar and Data Scientist - NLP/ML

Current

University of Central Florida, Orlando, FL

- Natinonal Academies of Sciences research grant, Postdoctoral Researcher.
- GIS/ML integration with coastal housing vulnerability systems development.
- NLP Dynamic Topic Modeling for common-pool resource management.

Graduate Research Associate

2020

Kurdish Political Studies Program - UCF, Orlando, FL

- Data management and analysis.
- KPSP speakers, scholarship and event logistical support.

Adjunct Lecturer

2019 - 2020

School of Politics, Security, and International Affairs - UCF, Orlando, FL

POS 4764 - GIS for Political Analysis, Jupyter notebook repository

Graduate Research Associate

2018 - 2019

Intelligence Community's Center for Academic Excellence - UCF, Orlando, FL

- Design and development of data website: Psychological Characteristics of Leaders (PsyCL)
- Managed RA team collection of longitudinal, cross-national leader speech materials.

Researcher

2018

Secure Fisheries - One Earth Future, Broomfield, CO

- Collaboration on the design and implementation of the Fisheries Conflict Database.
- Conduct machine coding, database management, data collection, processing and analysis.

Graduate Teaching Assistant

School of Politics, Security, and International Affairs - UCF, Orlando, FL

International Relations, Comparative Politics, Geography, Political Science, Public Policy

Research Assistant

2013 - 2014

Department of Political Science - AU, Auburn, AL

 Developed coding scheme and coded over 850 news articles to determine media perception of D.C. Mayor Marion Barry. Analyzed quantitative and qualitative data.

COMPUTER SKILLS

Programming: Python, SQL, ArcGIS, R, Stata

Data Science: Numpy, Pandas, Matplotlib, Jupyter, Scikit-learn, NLTK, GeoPandas

"Introducing the Commons Synthesis Project: Topics and trends in the study of **PUBLICATIONS** 2021 common-pool resource" International Journal of the Commons. Joshua E. Lambert, Graham Epstein, Jennifer Joel, and Jacopo Baggio. 2021 "The Causes and Consequences of Fisheries Conflict around the Horn of Africa" forthcoming - Journal of Peace Research. Sarah M. Glaser, Colleen Devlin, Joshua E. Lambert, and Ciera Villegas. 2021 "Presidential Personalities and Operational Codes: Learning Effects and Midterm Congressional Election Results" Book Chapter in Operational Code Analysis and Foreign Policy Roles Crossing Simons Bridge. Joshua E. Lambert, Mark Schafer, Stephen Walker, and Collin Kazazis. 2021 "Psychological Characteristics of Leaders (PsyCL): Introducing a New Data Set" Under Review, Mark Schafer and Joshua E. Lambert. 2021 "What belief in extraterrestrial visitors to Earth reveals about trust in elections" The Conversation. Joshua E. Lambert and Anthony Licciardi. 2019 "Reassessing Private Military and Security Company(PMSC) 'Competition' in Civil War: Lessons from Sierra Leone" Small Wars and Insurgencies. Christopher M. Faulkner, Joshua E. Lambert, and Jonathan Powell. "Reassessing Rebellion" One Earth Future. Eric Keels, Jay Benson, John Filitz, 2019 and Joshua E. Lambert. 2019 "Why Sudan's deadly crackdown on protesters could escalate in coming weeks" The Conversation. Eric Keels and Joshua E. Lambert. 2019 "Peeling back the layers on the role of private security companies in Africa" The Conversation. Christopher Faulkner, Joshua E. Lambert, and Jonathan Powell. 2018 "Fish Wars: The Causes and Consequences of Fisheries Conflict in Tanzania" One Earth Future. Sarah M. Glaser, Colleen Devlin, Joshua E. Lambert, Ciera Villegas, and Natasia Poinsatte. 2018 "Rulers, Elections, and Irregular Governance (REIGN) Showcase: Part I" One Earth Future. Clayton Besaw, Joshua E. Lambert, and Jean-Pierre Larroque. "Global Patterns in Religion and Large Scale Violence" (With Güneş Murat Tezcür) WORKING **PAPERS** "Coup-Proofing, Mutinies, and Private Military and Security Companies" (with Christopher Faulkner) "Them Belly Full but We Hungry: Food Insecurity as an Elite Motivator for Coups" **CONFERENCE** 2021

International Studies Association (Remote)

International Studies Association (Toronto, CAN)

International Studies Association (Cancelled - Honolulu, HI)

Florida Political Science Association (Orlando, FL); Southwestern Political Science Association (Austin, TX); International Society of Political Psychology Association

(Edinburgh, SCT); International Studies Association South (Orlando, FL)

Alabama Political Science Association (Montgomery, AL); Southern Political

Southern Political Science Association (New Orleans, LA)

PARTICIPATION

2020

2019

2018

2017

2014

Science	Association	New	Orleans	LA)
ocience	rissociation	(TACAA	Officalis,	L/1)

2013 Alabama Political Science Association (Tuscaloosa, AL)

RESEARCH	
INTERESTS	

Conflict, Environmental Security, Civil-Military Relations, Political Psychology,

Data Mining, Remote Sensing, Forecasting

SERVICE

President - Political Science Graduate Student Association (UCF)2018 - 2019Vice President - Student Government Association (UNO)2015Member - Dean Search Committee (UNO)2015Senator - Student Government Association (UNO)2014 - 2015

AWARDS & PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT

2020	ViEWS Conflict Forecasting Competition invited participant	Uppsala, SWE
2018	PRIO Conflict Trends Course participant	Oslo, NOR
2018	SciPy conference workshop participant	Austin, TX
2017	GEOINT Symposium participant	Tampa Bay, FL
2017	DIA Summer Seminar participant	Washington D.C.
2017	UCF Political Science Colloquium presenter	Orlando, FL
2017	Florida Political Science Graduate Paper Winner	Orlando, FL
2017	ISPP Summer Methodology Academy participant	Edinburgh, SCT
2015	UNO Student Government Senator of the year	New Orleans, LA

REFERENCES

Jonathan Powell | Committee Chair

Associate Professor

School of Politics, Security, and International Affairs

University of Central Florida Jonathan.Powell@ucf.edu

407-823-2082

Konstantin Ash | Committee Co-Chair

Assistant Professor

School of Politics, Security, and International Affairs

University of Central Florida Konstantin.Ash@ucf.edu 407-823-2608

Peter Jacques | Committee Member

Professor

School of Politics, Security, and International Affairs

University of Central Florida

Peter.Jacques@ucf.edu

407-823-6773

Güneş Murat Tezcür | Supervisor

Professor and Jalal Talabani Chair of Kurdish Political Studies

School of Politics, Security, and International Affairs

University of Central Florida

Tezcur@ucf.edu

407-823-2040